<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A worke of the Beast or A relation of a most vnchristian censure, executed vpon Iohn Lilburne, (novv prisoner in the fleet) the 18 of Aprill 1638 With the heavenly speech vttered by him at the time of his fuffering [sic]. Uery vsefull for these times both for the encouragement of the godly to suffer, and for the terrour and shame of the Lords adversaries.</title>
            <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1638</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 79 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05467</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15599</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108558</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844216</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844216</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9007</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05467)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9007)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 843:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A worke of the Beast or A relation of a most vnchristian censure, executed vpon Iohn Lilburne, (novv prisoner in the fleet) the 18 of Aprill 1638 With the heavenly speech vttered by him at the time of his fuffering [sic]. Uery vsefull for these times both for the encouragement of the godly to suffer, and for the terrour and shame of the Lords adversaries.</title>
                  <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>30, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Richt Right Press],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Amsterdam] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>in the yeare the Beast was wounded 1638.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Identification of printer and place of publication from STC.</note>
                  <note>WIth a final leaf of verse.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9007:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9007:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A WORKE OF THE BEAST OR A Relation of a moſt vnchriſtian Cenſure, Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vpon IOHN LILBVRNE, (Novv priſoner in the fleet) the <hi>18</hi> of Aprill <hi>1638.</hi> With the heavenly ſpeech vttered by him at the time of his ſuffering.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uery vſefull for theſe times both for the encouragement of the Godly to ſuffer, And for the terrour and ſhame of the Lords Adverſaries.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>HEB. <hi>10.36.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>For you have neede of patience, that after you have don the will of God, you might receiue the promiſes</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>HEB. <hi>11.36.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>And others had triall of cruell mockings, and ſcourgings yea moreover of bands and impriſonments.</p>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <head>RIGHT RICHT</head>
               <figDesc>crest or blazon</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed in the yeare the Beaſt was Wounded 1638</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publisher_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:9007:2"/>
            <head>The Publiſher to the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Tender hearted Reader.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>OF The wicked it is truely ſaid in <hi>Iob.</hi> their <hi>Light ſhalbee Put out:</hi> Now wee ſee, in a <hi>Candle,</hi> beeing almoſt extinguiſhed, that after it hath glimmered a while, it rayſeth ſome few blazing flaſhes, and ſoe ſuddenly vaniſheth.</p>
            <p>To ſpeake what I thinke, my minde gives me, that the Lord is now vpon extinguiſhing the bloody Prelates out of our Land. For whereas they have not, in ſome late yeares ſhewed the cruelty which they did before, but now increaſe in perſecution; me thinkes this is a cleere fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going ſigne, that (like a <hi>ſnuffe</hi> in the <hi>ſocket</hi>) their end and ruine is at hand.</p>
            <p>I write this, to have thee the more patient, contented, and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, when thou either heareſt, ſeeſt, or readeſt of their barbarous crueltie; beſure their condemnation ſleepeth not, but when their wickednes is full, I ſay when they haue once filled up the meaſure of their iniquity the which I truſt they haue allmoſt don) then will the Lord ſend back theſe <hi>locuſts</hi> to the <hi>Bottomleſſe pitt,</hi> from whence they came.</p>
            <p>In the meane time feare not their faces, but ſtand in the trueth, and let Gods houſe and his ordinances bee deare to thy ſoule, And know, that as the Lord gaue ſtrength to this his Servant to ſuffer joyfully for Chriſts cauſe; ſoe he will to thee and me and all others of his ſaints, if he count us worthy to be called thereto.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine if thou be Chriſts, and a hater of the Engliſh Popiſh Prelates. <hi>F. R.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:9007:2"/>
            <head>A WORKE OF THE BEAST, OR A Relation of a moſt unchriſtian Cenſure, executed vpon IOHN LILBVRNE, (Novv priſoner in the fleet) the <hi>18.</hi> of Aprill <hi>1638</hi> vvith the heavenly ſpeech vtter by him at the time of his ſuffering.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Pon Wedneſday the ſaid 18 of Aprill, Hauing noe certaine notice of the execution of my Cenſure, till this preſent morning, I prepared my ſelfe by prayer unto God, that he would make good his promiſe, to be vvith me &amp; enable me to undergoe my Affliction vvith joyfullnes &amp; courage: and that he vvould bee a mou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h and vtterance vnto mee to enable me to ſpeake that vvhich might make for his greateſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. And in my meditations my ſoule did principally pitch vpon theſe Three places of Scripture.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That in <hi>Jſay.</hi> 41.10.11.12.13. <hi>Feare thou not for I am with thee, be not diſmaid for I am thy God, I will ſtrengthen thee, yea I will helpe thee, yea I will uphold thee with the right hand of my righteouſnes. Behold all they that were incenced against thee ſhall be aſhamed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, they ſhall be as nothing, and they that ſtriue with thee ſhall perriſh. Thou ſhalt ſeeke them &amp; ſhall not finde them, even them that contented with thee, they that warr against thee ſhall be as nothing &amp; as a thing of nought. For I the Lord thy God will hold thee by thy right hand, ſaying vnto thee, feare not, J will helpe thee, Feare not thou worme Jacob, and yee men of Iſraell, I will helpe, thee ſayth the Lord and thy Redeemer the Holy one of Iſraell. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, that place in <hi>Iſay,</hi> 43.1.2. Where God ſpeaks thus to his Elect. <hi>Feare not for J have Redeemed thee, I have called thee by thy name thou art mine. When thou paſſest through the waters J wilbe with thee, and though the rivers they ſhall not overflow thee, when thou wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt through the fire thou ſhalt not bee burnt, neither ſhall the flame kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ell vpon thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:9007:3"/>Thirdly, that in <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5.6. In theſe words <hi>For he hath ſayd I will never leave thee nor forſake thee, Soe that we may boldly ſay the Lord is my helper, J will not feare what man can doe to me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With the conſideration of theſe and other gratious promiſes, made to his people, I being one of his choſen ones, did claime my ſhare &amp; intereſt in them, and the Lord of his infinite goodnes en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled me to caſt my ſelfe upon and reſt in them, knowing and ſtedfaſtly beleeving that he is a God of faithfullnes and power, whoe is able and willing to make good theſe his promiſes to the vtmoſt, and (to his praiſe be it ſpoken I deſire to ſpeake it) my ſoule was that morning exceedingly lifted up with ſpiritual con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation: and J felt within me ſuch a divine ſupportation, that the baſeneſſe of my puniſhment J was to undergoe did ſeem as a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of nothing to me. And I went to my ſuffering with as willing and joyfull a heart as if J had been going to ſolemnize the day of my maraige with one of the choyſeſt Creatures this world could afford. The Warden of the Fleete hauing ſent his men for my old fellow ſouldier. <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Iohn Wharton,</hi> and my ſelfe being both in one Chamber, wee made our ſelues readie to goe to the place of execution. I tooke the old man by the hand and led him downe three payre of ſtayers, and ſoe along the yard till we came to the Gate. And when we came there <hi>George Harrington</hi> the Porter told me J muſt ſtay alitle, and after our parting (commending one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other to the protection of our alſufficient God) I was bid goe to the Porters Lodge, noe ſooner was I gone in, but came <hi>Iohn Hawes,</hi> the other Porter to me vſing theſe words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr Lilburne,</hi> I am very ſorie for your puniſhment, you are now to undergoe, you muſt ſtripp you, and be whipt from hence to <hi>Westminſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I replied, the will of my God be done, for I knowe he will car<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry me through it with an vndaunted Spirit; But I muſt confeſſe it ſeemed at the firſt a little ſtrange to me, in regard <hi>I</hi> had no more notice given me for my preperation for ſoe ſore a puniſhment. For I thought I ſhould not haue been whipt through the ſtreete but onely at the Pillory. And ſoe paſſing a long the Lane being attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:9007:3"/>
with many Staves and Halberts, as Chriſt was when he was apprehended by his Enimies and led to the <hi>High Priests Hall. Mat.</hi> 26, we came to ffleete-bridge where was a Cart ſtanding ready for me. And I being commanded to ſtripp me, I did it with all willingnes and cheerefullnes, where upon the executioner tooke out a Corde and tyed my hands to the Carts Arſſe, which cauſed me to vtter theſe words, <hi>Wellcome be the Croſſe of Christ,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With that there drew neere a Yong man of my acquentance, and bid me put on a Couragious reſolution to ſuffer cheerfully &amp; not to diſhonor my cauſe for you ſuffer (ſaid he) for a good cauſe, I gaue him thanks, for his chriſtian incouragement, J replying I know the cauſe is good, for it is Gods cauſe, &amp; for my own part I am cheerful &amp; merry in the Lord, &amp; am as well contented with this my preſent portion as if I were to receiue my preſent liberty. For I knowe my God that hath gone along with me hither to, will carry me though to the end. And for the affliction itſelf, though it be the puniſhment in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted upon Rogues. yet I eſteeme it not the leaſt diſgrace, but the greateſt honour that can be done unto me, that the Lord counts me worthy to ſuffer any thing for his great name;</p>
            <p>And you my Brethren that doe now here behold my preſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition this day, be not diſcouraged, be not diſcouraged at the waies of Godlineſſe by reaſon of the Croſſe which accompanies it, for it is the lot and portion of all which will liue Godly in Chriſt Ieſus to ſuffer perſecution,</p>
            <p>The Cart being readie to goe forward. I ſpake to the executioner (when I ſaw him pull out his Corded whipp out of his pocket) after this manner, Well my friend doe thy office. To which he replyed I haue whipt many a Rogue but now I ſhall whip an honeſt man, but be not diſcouraged (ſaid he) it will be ſoon over.</p>
            <p>To which I replyed, J knowe my God hath not onely enabled me to beleeve in his name, but alſoe to ſuffer for his ſake. Soe the Carman drove forward his Cart, and I laboured with my God for ſtrength to ſubmit my back with cheerfullnes unto the ſmitter. And he heard my deſire &amp; granted my requeſt, for when the firſt ſtripe was giuen I felt not the leaſt paine but ſaid, <hi>Bleſſed be thy name O Lord my God that haſt counted mee worthy to ſuffer for</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:9007:4"/>
thy glorious names ſake; And at the giving of the ſecond, I cried out with a loud voice <hi>Hallelujah, Hallelujah, Glory, Honour, and Praiſe, bee given to thee O Lord for ever, and to the Lambe that ſitts vpon the Throne.</hi> Soe wee vvent vp <hi>Fleetstreete,</hi> the Lord enabling me to endure the ſtripes vvith ſuch patience and chere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullnes, that <hi>J</hi> did not in the leaſt manner ſhevv the leaſt diſcontent at them, for my God hardened my backe, and ſteeled my reynes, and tooke a vvay the ſmart and payne of the ſtripes from mee.</p>
            <p>But <hi>J</hi> muſt confeſſe, if I had had no more but my owne naturall ſtrength, I had ſuncke vnder the burden of my puniſhement, for to the fleſh the paine was uery grevious &amp; heauy: But my God in whom I did truſt was higher and ſtronger then my ſelfe, whoe ſtrengthened and enabled mee not onely to undergoe the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with cherefullnes: but made me Triumph &amp; with a holy diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>daine to inſult over my torments.</p>
            <p>And as we went along the Strand, many friends ſpoke to me &amp; aſked how I did, &amp; bid me be cherfull, to whom I replied, I was mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and cheerfull: and was upheld with a diuine and heauenly ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation, comforted with the ſweet conſolations of Gods ſpirit. And about the middle of the Strand, there came a Friend and bid me ſpeake with boldneſſe. To when I replied, when the time comes ſoe I will<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for then if I ſhould haue ſpoken and ſpent my ſtrength, it would haue been but as water ſpilt on the ground, in regard of the noyſe and preſſe of people. And alſoe at that time I was not in a fitt temper to ſpeake: becauſe the duſt much troubled mee, and the Sunne ſhined very hot vpon mee. And the Tipſtaffe man at the firſt vvould not let mee haue my hatt to keepe the vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment heate of the Sunne from my head. Alſoe hee many times ſpake to the Cart man to driue ſoftly, Soe that the heate of the Sunne exceedingly peirced my head: and made me ſomwhat faint. But yet my God vpheld me vvith courage, and made me vndergoe it vvith a joyfull heart. And vvhen J came to Chearing Croſſe ſome <hi>Christian friends</hi> ſpake to me and bid me be of good cheere.</p>
            <p>Soe <hi>I</hi> am (ſaid <hi>I</hi>) for I reſt not in my ovvne ſtrength. but <hi>J</hi> fight vnder the Banner of my great and mightie <hi>Captaine the Lord
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:9007:4"/>
Jeſus Chriſt</hi> who hath conquered all his Enemies, and I doubt not but through his ſtrength I ſhall conquer and over come all my ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, for his power upholdes mee, his ſtrength enables mee, his preſence cheeres mee, and his Spirit comforts mee, and I looke for an immortall Crowne which never ſhall fade nor decay. the aſſured hope and expectation where of makes, mee to contemne my ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, and count them as nothing, ffor my momentany affliction will worke for me a farre more exceeding Crowne and weight of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. And as I went by the Kings pallace a great Multitude of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple came to looke vpon me. And paſſing through the gate vnto <hi>Westminster,</hi> Many demanded what was the matter.</p>
            <p>To whom I replied, my Brethren, againſt the Law of God, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the law of the Land, againſt the King or State haue J not committed the leaſt offence that deſerves this puniſhment, but only J ſuffer as an object of the Prelates cruelty and malice; and hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, one of the <hi>Warden</hi> of the <hi>Fleets-officers,</hi> beganne to interrupt me, and tells mee my ſuffering was juſt and therefore I ſhould hold my tongue; Whom J bidd meddle with his owne buſineſſe, for I would ſpeake come what would, for my cauſe was good for which I ſuffered, and here I was ready to ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>d my deareſt blood for it.</p>
            <p>And as we went through <hi>Kings ſtreet,</hi> many encouraged me, and bidd me be cheerefull; Others whoſe faces (to my knwoledge) I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſawe before, and who J verilie thinke knew not the cauſe of my ſuffering, but ſeeing my cheerefullnes vnder it, beſeeched the Lord to bleſſe me and ſtrenthen mee.</p>
            <p>At the laſt wee came to the Pillary, where I was unlooſed from the <hi>Cart,</hi> and having put one ſome of my cloathes wee went to the <hi>Taverne,</hi> vvhere J ſtaid a prittie vvhile vvaiting for my Surgeon.</p>
            <p>vvhoe vvas not yet come to dreſſe mee. Where vvere many of my Friends, whoe exceedingly rejoyced to ſee my courage. that the Lord had enabled me to vndergoe my puniſhment ſoe willingly.</p>
            <p>Whoe aſked me how I did. I tould them, as well as ever I was in my life I bleſſe my God for it. for I felt ſuch inward joy and comfort, chearing vp my ſoule, that I lightly eſteemed my ſufferings.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:9007:5"/>And this I counted my weding day in which I was married to the Lord Ieſus Chriſt: for now I knowe he loues me in that he hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed ſoe rich apparrell this day upon me, and counted me wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to ſuffer for his ſake. I hauing a deſire to retire into a private roome from the multitude of people that were about me, which made me like to faint: I had not been ther long but <hi>Mr. Lightburne</hi> the Tibſtaſſe of the <hi>Star-Chamber,</hi> came to me ſaying the <hi>Lords</hi> ſent him to me, to knowe if I would acknowledge my ſelfe to be in a fault and then he knew what to ſay unto me. To whom I replied, Haue their Honours cauſed me to be whipt from the Fleet to Weſtminſter, and doe they now ſend to knowe if I wil acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge a fault. They ſhould have done this before I had beene whipt; for now ſeeing I have vndergone the greateſt part of my pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, I hope the Lord will aſſiſt me to goe through it all, and beſides, if I would haue done this at the firſt I needed not to haue come to this, But as I tould the Lords when J was before them at the Barre. Soe I deſire you to tell them againe, that I am not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious to my ſelfe of doing any thing that deſerues a ſubmiſſion, but yet I doe willingly ſubmit to their Lordſhips pleaſures in my Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. He told me if I would confeſſe, a fault it would ſaue me a-ſtanding on the Pillary otherwiſe I muſt undergoe the burden of it.</p>
            <p>Wel, I (Said I) J regard not a little outward diſgrace for the cauſe of my God, I haue found alreadie that ſweetneſſe in him in whom I haue beleeued, that through his ſtrength I am able to undergoe any thing that ſhalbee inflicted on me; But me thinks that J had verie hard meaſure that I ſhould be condemned and thus puniſhed vpon two Oaths in which the party hath moſt falſlie foreſworne him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: and becauſe I would not take an Oath to betray mine owne innocency; Why <hi>Paul</hi> found more favour and mercy from the Heathen <hi>Roman-Governors,</hi> for they would not put him to an Oath to accuſe himſelfe, but ſuffered him to make the beſt defence he could for himſelfe, neither would they condemne him before his accuſers and he were brought face to face, to juſtifie and fully to proue their accuſation: But the Lords haue not dealt ſo with me, for my accuſers and I were neuer brought face to to face to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie their accuſation againſt me: it is true two falſe Oathes were
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:9007:5"/>
Sworne againſt mee: and I was therevpon condemned, and becauſe I would not accuſe my ſelfe. It is true (ſaid hee) it was ſoe with <hi>Paul</hi> but the Lawes of this Land, are otherwiſe then their Lawes were in thoſe dayes. Then ſaid I, they are vvorſe and more cruell, then the Lawes of the <hi>Pagans</hi> and <hi>Heathen Romans</hi> were, whoe would condemne no man without wittneſſes, and they ſhould be brought face to face, to juſtifie their accuſation. And ſo hee went away, &amp; I prepared my ſelfe for the Pillary, to which J went with a joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full courage, and when I was vpon it, I made obeyſance to the <hi>Lords,</hi> ſome of them as (J ſuppoſe) looking out at the <hi>Sarr-Chamber</hi>-window, towards mee. And ſo I putt my neck into the hole, which beeing a great deale to low for me, it was very painfull to me in regard of the continuance of time that I ſtood on the Pillary: which was about two houres, my back alſo being very ſore, and the Sunne ſhining exceeding hot. And the <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pſtaffe man,</hi> not ſuffering mee to keepe on my hat, to defend my head from the heat of the Sunne. So that I ſtood there in great paine. Yet through the ſtrength of my God I vnderwent it with courage: to the very laſt minute. And lifting vp my heart and ſpirit vnto my God,</p>
            <p>While I was thus ſtanding on the Pillary. J craued his Power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full aſſiſtance with the ſpirit of wiſdome and courage, that I might open my mouth with boldneſſe: and ſpeake thoſe things that might make for his greateſt glory, and the good of his people, and ſoe caſting my eyes on the multitude, I beganne to ſpeake after this manner.</p>
            <p>My <hi>Christean Brethren,</hi> to all you that loue the Lord Ieſus Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and deſire that hee ſhould raigne and rule in your hearts and liues, to you eſpecially: and to as many as heare me this day: I direct my ſpeech.</p>
            <p>J ſtand here in the place of ignominy and ſhame. Yet to mee it is not ſo, but I owne and imbrace it, as the <hi>Wellcome Croſſe of Christ.</hi> And as a badge of my <hi>Chriſtian Profeſſion.</hi> I haue been already whipt from the Fleet to this place, by vertue of a Cenſure: from the <hi>Honourable Lords</hi> of the <hi>Starr Chamber</hi> hereunto, The Cauſe of my Cenſure I ſhall declare unto you as briefly as I canne.</p>
            <p>The Lord by his ſpeciall hand of prouidence ſo ordered it, that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:9007:6"/>
Not long agoe I was in <hi>Holland.</hi> Where I was like to haue ſettled my ſelfe in a Courſe of trading, that might haue brought me in a-pretty large portion of earthlie things; (after which my heart did too much runne) but the Lord hauing a better portion in ſtore for mee, and more durable riches to beſtow vpon my ſoule. By the ſame hand of providence: brought me back a gaine. And caſt me into eaſie affliction, that there by I might be weaned from the world, and ſee the vanitie and emptines of all things therein. And he hath now pitched my ſoule vpon ſuch an object of beautie, amiableneſſe: &amp; excelencie, as is as permanent and endurable as eternitie it ſelfe, Namely the perſonall excelencie of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt. the ſweetneſſe of whoſe preſence, no affliction can ever be able to wreſt out of my ſoule.</p>
            <p>Now while J was in <hi>Holland,</hi> it ſeemes ther were divers Bookes. of that Noble and Renowned <hi>Dr. Iohn Bastwicks</hi> ſent into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> which came to the hands of one <hi>Edmond Chillington,</hi> for the ſending over which I was taken, and apprehended, the plot being before laid, by one <hi>Iohn Chilliburne</hi> (whom I ſuppoſed) &amp; tooke to be my friend) ſervant to my old fellow ſouldier <hi>Mr. John Wharton</hi> living in <hi>Bow-lane</hi> (after this manner.)</p>
            <p>I walking in the Street, with the ſaid <hi>Iohn Chilliburne,</hi> was taken by the <hi>Purſevant</hi> and his men. the ſaid <hi>Iohn</hi> as I verily beleeve, hauing given direction to them: where to ſtand, and he himſelfe was the third man that laid hands on me to hold mee.</p>
            <p>Now at my Cenſure before the <hi>Lords:</hi> I there declared vpon the word of <hi>a Christian</hi> that I ſent not over thoſe Bookes, neither did I know the Shipp that brought them. nor any of the men that belonged to the Shipp, nor to my knowledge did I ever ſee, either Shipp: or any appertaining to it, in all my dayes.</p>
            <p>Beſides this, I was accuſed at my examination before, the <hi>Kings Atturny</hi> at his Chamber, by the ſaid <hi>Edmond Chillington</hi> Button Seller Iiving in <hi>Canon ſtreet</hi> neere <hi>Abchurch Lane,</hi> and late Priſoner in <hi>Bridewell</hi> &amp; <hi>Newgate,</hi> for printing 10. or 12. thouſand Bookes in <hi>Holland,</hi> and that J would haue printed <hi>the Vnmasking the miſtery of iniquitie</hi> if I could haue gott a true Copie of it, and that I had a Chamber in <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. John Foots</hi> houſe at <hi>Delfe</hi> where hee thinkes
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:9007:6"/>
the bookes were kept. Now here I declare before you all, vpon the word of a ſuffering Chriſtian: that hee might haue as well accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed mee of printing a hundred thouſand bookes, and the on been as true as the other; And for the printing the <hi>Vnmaſking the Mistery of Iniquity,</hi> vpon the word of an honeſt man I never ſaw, nor to my knowledge heard of the Booke, till I came back againe into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> And for my having a Chamber in <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. John Foots</hi> houſe at <hi>Delfe,</hi> where he thinkes the Bookes were kept. J was ſoe farre from having a Chamber there, as I never lay in his houſe, but twice or thrice at the moſt, and upon the laſt Friday of the laſt Tearme I was brought to the <hi>Star-Chamber Barre,</hi> where before mee was read the ſaid <hi>Edmond Chillingtons Affidavit,</hi> vpon Oath, againſt <hi>Mr. John Wharton</hi> and my ſelfe. The Summe of which Oath was, That hee and I had Printed (at <hi>Rotterdam</hi> in <hi>Holland,) Dr. Baſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wicks Anſwer,</hi> and his <hi>Letany,</hi> with divers other ſcandalous Bookes.</p>
            <p>Now here againe I ſpeake it in the preſence of God, &amp; all you that heare mee, that <hi>Mr. Wharton,</hi> and I never joyned together in printing, either theſe or any other Bookes whatſoever. Neither did I receive any mony from him, toward the printing any.</p>
            <p>Withall, in his firſt Oath, hee peremtorilie ſwore that wee had printed them at <hi>Rotterdam.</hi> Vnto which I likewiſe ſay, That hee hath in this particular forſworne himſelfe, for my owne part, I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in all my daies either printed, or cauſed to be printed, either for my ſelfe or <hi>Mr. Wharton</hi> any Bookes at <hi>Rotterdam.</hi> Neither did I come into any Printing houſe there all the time I was in the Citty.</p>
            <p>And then vpon the Tweſday after he ſwore, againſt both of us agai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. The ſumme of which Oaths was, that I had confeſſed to him (which is moſt falſe) that I had Printed <hi>Dr. Baſtwicks</hi> Anſwer to <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. John Banks</hi> his <hi>Information,</hi> and his <hi>Letany;</hi> &amp; another Booke called <hi>Certaine anſwers to certaine Objections;</hi> And another Booke cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led <hi>The vanity &amp; impiety of the old Letany;</hi> &amp; that J had divers other Bookes of the ſaid <hi>Dr. Baſtwicks</hi> in Printing, &amp; that <hi>Mr. Wharton</hi> had beene at the charges of Printing a Booke called <hi>A Breviat,</hi> of the Biſhops late proceeding; and another Booke called 16. <hi>new Queries,</hi> and in this his Oath hath ſworne they were Printed at <hi>Rot<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terdam,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:9007:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
or ſome where elſe in <hi>Holland;</hi> &amp; that on <hi>James Oldam.</hi> a Turner keping Shop at <hi>Weſtminſter-hall-gate</hi> diſperced divers of theſe bookes. Now in this Oath he hath againe forſworne himſelfe in a high degree, for wheras he took his Oath that I had printed the Booke called <hi>The Vanitie and impiety of the old Letany,</hi> I here ſpeake it before you all, that I never in all my daies did ſee one of them in print, but I muſt confeſs, I haue ſeen &amp; read it, in written hand, before the Dr. was cenſured, &amp; as for other books, of which he ſaith I haue diverſe in printing. To that I anſwer, that for mine owne perticuler I never read nor ſaw any of the <hi>Drs.</hi> Bookes: but the forenamed foure in Engliſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and one little thing more of about two ſheetes of paper, which is annexed to the <hi>Vanity of the Old Letany,</hi> And as for his Lattine Bookes J never ſaw any but two: Namely his <hi>Flagellum,</hi> for which he was firſt cenſured in the <hi>High Commiſſion Court:</hi> and his <hi>Apologeticus,</hi> which were both in print long before J knew the Dr. But it is true, there is a ſecond edition of his <hi>Flagellum,</hi> but that was at the preſſe aboue two yeares agoe: namly Anno 1634. And ſome of this impreſſion was in England before J came out of Holland,</p>
            <p>And theſe are the maine things for which I was Cenſured and Condemned. Being two Oaths in which the ſaid <hi>Chillington,</hi> hath palpably forſworne himſelfe. And if hee had not forſworne himſelfe. Yet by the law (as I am given to vnderſtand) I might have excepted againſt him, being a guilty perſon himſelfe and a Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and did that which hee did againſt mee for pvrcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his owne liberty which hee hath by ſuch Iudaſly meanes gott and obtained. Who is alſo knowne to bee a lying fellow, as J told the Lords I was able to proue and make good.</p>
            <p>But beſides all this, there was an inquiſition-Oath-tendered vnto mee (which J refuſed to take) on foure ſeverall daies; the ſumme of which Oath is thus much. You ſhall ſweare that you ſhall make true anſwer to all things that ſhall be aſked of you: So helpe you God. Now this Oath I refuſed as a ſinfull and vnlawfull Oath: it being the <hi>High-Commiſſion Oath,</hi> with which the Prelates euer haue and ſtill do ſo butcherly torment, afflict and vndoe, the deare Saints and Servants of God, It is alſo an Oath againſt the Law of the Land,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:9007:7"/>
As <hi>Mr. Nicholas Fuller</hi> in his Argument doth proue. And olſo it is expreſſly againſt the <hi>Petition of Right an Act of Parlament Enacted</hi> in the ſecond yeare of our King. Againe, it is abſolutely againſt the Law of God, for that law requires noe man to accuſe himſelfe, but if any thing be laid to his charge: there muſt come two or three witneſſes at the leaſt to proue it. It is alſo againſt the practiſe of Chriſt himſelfe, who in all his examinations before the High Prieſt would not accuſe himſelfe: but vpon their demands, returned this anſwer: <hi>Why aſke yea mee, go to them that heard mee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With all this Oath is againſt the uery law of nature, for nature is alwaies a preſerver of it ſelfe and not a diſtroyer. But if a man takes this wicked Oath he diſtroyes and vndoes himſelfe, as daily experience doth witneſſe. Nay it is worſe then the Law of the Heathen Romans, as we may reade <hi>Act.</hi> 25.16. <hi>For when Paull ſtood before the Pagan Governours, and the laws required Judgement againſt him, the Governour replyed, it is not the manner of the Romans to condemne any man before his accuſers &amp; hee were brought face to face to justify their accuſation.</hi> But for my owne part, if I had beene pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded againſt by a Bill, J would haue anſwered &amp; juſtified all that they coulde have proved againſt me, &amp; by the ſtrength of my God would have ſealed whatſoever I have don with my bloud, for <hi>I</hi> am privy to mine own actions, &amp; my conſcience beares me witnes that I have laboured ever ſince the Lord in mercy made the riches of his grace known to my Soule, to keep a good conſcience and to walke inoffenſably both towards God, &amp; man. But as for that Oath that was put unto me <hi>I</hi> did refuſe to take it, as a ſinfull and unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Oath, &amp; by the ſtrength of my God enabling me <hi>I</hi> wil never take it though <hi>I</hi> be pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d in peices with wilde horſes as the ancient Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians were by the bloudy Tirants, in the <hi>Primitive Church,</hi> neither ſhall I thinke that man a faithfull Subject, of Chriſts Kingdome, that ſhall at any time hereafter take it, ſeeing the wickednes of it hath been ſo apparently laid open by ſo many, for the refuſall wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of many doe ſuffer cruell perſecution to this day. Thus have <hi>J</hi> as briefly as I could; declared unto you, the whole cauſe of my ſtanding here this day, I being upon theſe grounds cenſured by the Lords at the <hi>Starr-chamber</hi> on the laſt Court day of the laſt tearme to pay 500. po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the King and to receive the puniſhment which with rejoicing I haue undergon, vnto whoſe cenſure I do with willingnes &amp; cheerefulnes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mit, my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:9007:8"/>But ſeeing I now ſtand here at this preſent, I intend the Lord aſſiſting me with his power, and guiding me by his ſpirit, to declare my minde unto you.</p>
            <p>I haue nothing to ſay to any mans perſon, and therefore will not meddle with that. Onlie the things that I have to ſay in the firſt place, are concerning the <hi>Biſhops</hi> &amp; their calling. They challeng their callings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o be <hi>Iure Divino,</hi> &amp; for the oppugning of which, thoſe three renovvned living marters of the Lord, <hi>Dr. Baſtwick M. Burton</hi> &amp; <hi>M. Prinne:</hi> did ſuffer in this place, and they have ſufficientlie proved, that their, Calling is not from God, which men I love and honour, and doe perſwade my ſelfe their ſoules are deere and precious in the ſight of God, though they were ſo cruellie and but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherlie dealt with by the Prelates, and as for <hi>Mr. Burton</hi> and <hi>Mr. Prynne</hi> they are worthie and learned men, but yet did not in manie things write ſo fullie as the Dr. did, who hath ſufficientlie &amp; plen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tifullie ſet forth the wickednes, both of the Prelates themſelves &amp; of their callings<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (as you may reade in his Bookes) that they are not <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> which noble and reverend Dr. I love with my Soule<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and as he is a man that ſtands for the truth and Glorie of God, my verie life and hart blood I will lay downe for his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and the maintaining of his cauſe, for which he Suffered, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Gods cauſe. As for the Biſhops, they vſed in former times to chal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leng their juriſdiction, Callings, and power from the King. But they haue now openly in the <hi>High Commiſſion Court</hi> renounced that as was heard by many, at the Cenſure of that <hi>Noble Dr.</hi> And as you may fullie read in his <hi>Apollogeticus.</hi> And in his <hi>Anſwer</hi> to <hi>Sr. Iohn Bankes</hi> his <hi>Jnformation.</hi> Novv J will here mantaine it before them all. That their Calling is ſo farre from being <hi>Iure Diuino</hi> (as they ſay they are) that they are rather <hi>Iure Diabollico.</hi> Which if I be not able to proue, let me be hanged vp at the Hall Gate. But my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, for your better ſatiſfaction, read the 9. &amp; 13. <hi>Chapters</hi> of the <hi>Reuelation,</hi> and there you ſhall ſee, that there came <hi>Locust</hi> out of the <hi>Bottomleſſe Pitt,</hi> part of vvhom they are<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and they are ther liuely diſcirbed. Alſo you ſhall there finde, that the <hi>Beaſt</hi> (which is the <hi>Pope,</hi> or Roman State and Goverment.) hath given to him by the <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>agon</hi> (the <hi>Devill</hi>) his Power and Seate, and great authoritie.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:9007:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Soe that the <hi>Popes</hi> authoritie comes from the Devill, and the Prelates, and their Creatures in their printed Bookes, do challenge their authoritie juriſdiction and Power, (that they exerciſe over all ſorts of people) is from Rome.</p>
            <p>And for proving of the Church of England to be a true Church, their beſt &amp; ſtrongeſt argument is: that the Bb. are lineally diſcen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded from his Holines (or impiouſnes) of Rome: as you may read in <hi>Pocklingtons</hi> Booke, called <hi>Sunday no Sabboth.</hi> So that by their own confeſſion they ſtand by that ſame power and authoritie that they haue receaved from the <hi>Pope.</hi> Soe that their calling is not from God but from the Divill. For the Pope cannot give a better au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie or calling to them, then he himſelfe hath. But his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and Calling is from the Devill: Therefore the Prelates Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and authoritie is from the Devill alfoe. <hi>Revel.</hi> 9.3. <hi>And there came out of the ſmoake, Locuſts upon the earth: and unto them was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven power as the Scorpions of the earth haue power to hurt</hi> and vndoe men, as the Prelates dailie doe. And alſo <hi>Revel.</hi> 13.2. <hi>And the Beaſt which I ſawe</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Iohn) was like unto a Leopard, and his feete were as the feete of a Beare, and his mouth as the mouth of a Lion, and the Dragon</hi> (that is to ſay the Devill) <hi>gaue him his power, his ſeat, and great authority<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and <hi>ver.</hi> 15.16.17. And whether the Prelates as well as the Pope, do not daily the ſame things: let every man that hath but common reaſon judge.</p>
            <p>For do not their daily practiſes and cruell burdens, impoſed on all ſorts of people, high and low, rich and poore: witneſſe that their diſcent is from the Beaſt, part of his ſtate and kingdome. Soe alſo <hi>Revel.</hi> 16.13.14. All which places do declare, that their Power and authority being from the Pope, (as they themſelues con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſe) Therefore it muſt needes originally come from the Devill For their power &amp; callings, muſt of neceſſitie proceede either from God, or elſe from the Divill, But it proceeds not from God, as the Scriptures ſufficiently declares<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Therefore there calling and power proceeds from the Devill, as both Scripture and there owne daily practiſes doe demonſtrate and prove. And as for that laſt place ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.13.14. Jf you pleaſe to reade the Second, and third parts of <hi>Dr. Bastwicks Letany,</hi> you ſhall finde, he their proves that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:9007:9"/>
the Prelates practiſes doe every way ſuite with, and make good that portion of Scripture to the vtmoſt. For in their Sermons that they preach before his Majeſtie: how doe they incenſe the King &amp; nobles againſt the people of God, labouring to make them odious in his ſight &amp; ſtirring him up to execute vengance vpon them, though they be the moſt harmeleſſe generation of all others.</p>
            <p>And as for all theſe officers that are vnder them &amp; made by them, for mine own particular I cannot ſe but that their callings are as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull as the Biſhops themſelves, and in particular for the callings of the miniſters, J do not, nor will not ſpeake againſt their perſons, for I know ſome of them to be very able men, and men of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent guiftes and quallifications, and I perſwade my ſelfe their ſouls are very deare and pretious in the ſight of God.</p>
            <p>Yet not withſtanding, this proves not their Callings to be ever the better. As it is in civill government. If the King (whom God hath made a lawfull Majeſtrate) make a wicked man an officer, hee is as true an officer and as well to be obeyed, comming in the Kings name, as the beſt man in the world comming with the ſame atthori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, for in ſuch a caſe, he that is a wicked man hath his calling from as good authority as the godlieſt man hath: And therefore his call<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing is as good as the others.</p>
            <p>But on the other ſide, if he that hath noe authoritie make officers, though the men themſelues be never ſo good and holie. Yet their holines maks their calling never a whitt the truer, but ſtill is a falſe a calling: in regard his authority was not good nor lawful that made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; &amp; eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo the miniſters, be they never ſo holy me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: yet they haue one and the ſame calling with the wickedeſt that is amongeſt them, their holines proues not their callings to be ever the truer: ſeeing their authority that made them miniſters is falſe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they haue more to anſwer for then any of the reſt: by how much the more God hath beſtowed greater guifts vpon them then vpon others, and yet they detaine the truth in vnrighteouſneſſe from Gods people: and do not make knowne to them as they ought, the whole will and counſell of God.</p>
            <p>And againe, the greater is their ſinne if their callings be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull, (as J verily beleeve they are) in that they ſtill hold them
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:9007:9"/>
and doe not willingly lay them downe &amp; renounce them, for they do but deceiue the people and highly diſhonour God, and ſinne againſt their owne ſoules, while they preach vnto the people by ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue of an <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> and vnlawfull Calling, and the more god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and able the Miniſter is that ſtill preaches by vertue of this cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, the more hurt he doth, for the people that haue ſuch a Miniſter will not be perſwaded of the truth of things, though one ſpeake &amp; informe them in the name of the Lord; but will be ready to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, Our Miniſter that preaches ſtill by vertue of this Calling, is ſo ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly a man, that were not his calling right &amp; good: I do aſſure my ſelfe he would no longer preach by vertue thereof, And thus the holines of the miniſter is a Cloake to couer the unlawfulnes of his calling, and make the people continue rebells againſt Chriſts his Scepter and Kingdome, which is an agreuation of his ſinne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for by this meanes the people are kept off from receiving the whole truth into their ſoules, &amp; reſt in being but almoſt Chriſtians, or but Chriſtians in part. But Oh my Brethren, it behoues all you that feare God, and tender the Salvation of your owne Soules, to looke about you &amp; to ſhake of that long ſecurity &amp; formality in Religion, that you have layne in. For God of all things cannot indure <hi>Luke warmenes Revel</hi> 3.16. And ſearch out diligently the truth of things, and try them in the <hi>Ballance of the Sanctuary.</hi> I beſeech you take things no more vpon truſt, as hitherto you haue done, but take paines to ſearch and finde out thoſe Spirituall and hidden truthes that God hath enwraped in his ſacred Booke, and finde out a bottom for your owne ſoules. For if you will haue the comforts of them, you muſt beſtow ſome labour for the getting of them, and you muſt ſearch dilligently before you finde them <hi>Pro.</hi> 2. Labour alſo to withdraw your neckes from vnder that Spirituall and Antichriſtian bondage, (unto which you haue for a long time ſubjected your ſoules) leaſt the Lord cauſe his plagues and the fearceneſſe of his wrath to ſeize both vpon your bodies and ſoules: ſeeing you are now warned of the danger of theſe things.</p>
            <p>For hee himſelfe hath ſaid <hi>Revel. 14.9.10.11. That if any man worſhip the Boaſt and his Image, and receiue his marke in his forehead or in his hand. The ſame ſhall drinke of the wine of his wrath: which is
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:9007:10"/>
powered out without mixture into the cup of his indignation, and he ſhal be tormented with fire and brimſtone in the preſences of the holy Angels &amp; in the preſence of the Lambe, and the ſmoake of their Torment aſcended, vp for ever and ever, and they haue noe rest day nor night, who worſhip the Beaſt, &amp; his Image, and whoſoever receiveth the marke of his name.</hi> Therefore as you loue your owne ſoules and looke for that immor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tall Crowne of happines in the world to come, looke that you with draw your ſelves from that Antichriſtian power &amp; ſlavery that you are now vnder, even as God himſelfe hath commanded and injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned you in <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.4. ſaying <hi>Come out of her my people that you bee not pertaker of her ſinns and that yee receive not of her Plagues, for her ſinnes have reached vnto heaven, and God hath remembred her iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</hi> Here is the voyce of God himſelfe commanding all his cho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſen ones, though they have lived vnder this Antichriſtian ſlaviſh po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and eſtate along time, yet at laſt to withdraw their obedience, and ſubjection from it. My Brethren, wee are all at this preſent in a very dangerous and fearefull condition, vnder the Jdolatrous, and ſpirituall bondage of the Prelates, in regard wee have turned Traytours vnto our God, in ſeing his Almighty great name and his Heavenly truth troden under foote, and ſoe highlie diſhonoured by them, and yet wee not onely let them alone in holding our peace, but moſt ſlaviſhlie &amp; wickedly, ſubject our ſelves unto them, fearing the face of a peece of durt, more then the Almightie great God of Heaven and earth, who is able to caſt both body &amp; Soule in to everlaſting damnation.</p>
            <p>Oh repent, I beſeech you therefore repent, for that great diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour you have ſuffered to bee done unto God by your fearfullnes, and cowardlines, &amp; for the time to come, put on couragious reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions like valiant ſouldiers of <hi>Ieſus Christ,</hi> and fight manfullie in this his ſpirituall battell, in which battell ſome of his ſouldiers haue allready loſt part of their blood, and withall; Study this Booke of the <hi>Revol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion,</hi> and there you ſhall finde the miſtery of iniquitie fullie vnfolded and explaned; and alſo you ſhall ſe what great ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall battels haue beene fought betwixt the Lambe &amp; his Servants, and the <hi>Dragon</hi> (the <hi>Devill</hi>) and his vaſſals, and ſome are yet to fight.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:9007:10"/>Therefore gird on your Spirituall armour Spoken of <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6. that you may quit your ſelves like good &amp; faithfull Souldiers, and feare no coulors the victory and conqueſt is ours allready, for wee are ſure to have it, (I do not ſpeake of any bodily and temporall battell but onelie of a ſpirituall one) and be not diſcouraged and knoct of from the ſtudy of it, becauſe of the obſcurity and darkenes of it, for the Lord hath promiſed his enlightening Spirit unto all his people that are laborous and ſtudious to know him aright, and alſo he hath promiſed a bleſſing and pronounced a bleſſednes vnto all that read and labour to keepe the things contayned in this booke <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.3. My Chriſtian Brethren, in the bowels of Ieſus Chriſt I beſeech you doe not contemne the things that are delivered to you, in regard of the meaneſſe and weakneſſe of mee the inſtrument, being but one of the meaneſt and unworthieſt of the Servants of Jeſus Chriſt, for the Lord many times doth great things by weake meanes, that his power may be more ſeene, for wee are to ready to caſt our eye vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the meanes and inſtrument: not looking up unto that Almighty power that is in God, who is able to doe the greateſt things by the weakeſt meanes, and therefore out of the mouthes of <hi>Babes</hi> &amp; <hi>Suck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings</hi> he hath ordayned ſtrength <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8.2. And hee hath choſen the fooliſh things of the world to confound the wiſe, and God hath cho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſen the weake things of the world to confound the things which are mighty, &amp; baſe things of the world, &amp; things which are diſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed hath God choſen, Yea things which are not, to bring to nought things that are 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.27.28. And he giues the reaſon wherefore he is pleaſed ſo to do. <hi>That no fleſh ſhould glory in his preſence</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So you ſe God is not tyed to any inſtrument &amp; means to effect his own glory, but hee by the leaſt inſtrument is able to bring to paſſe the greateſt things.</p>
            <p>It is true, <hi>J</hi> am a yong man and noe Scoller, according to that which the world counts Scollerſhip, yet I have obtayned mercie of the Lord to be faithfull, &amp; hee by a divine prouidence hath brought me hither this day, &amp; I ſpeak to you in the name of the Lord, being aſſiſted with the ſpirit &amp; power of the God of Heaven and earth, &amp; I ſpeake not the words of raſhnes or inconſiderateneſſe, but the words of ſobernes, and mature deliberation, for I did conſult with my God before I came hither, and deſired him that he would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:9007:11"/>
and enable me to ſpeake that which might be for his glory and the good of his people, And as I am a Souldier fighting under the ban<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner of the great and mightie <hi>Captaine the Lord Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and as J looke for that Crowne of immortality which one day I know ſhall bee ſet upon my temples, being in the condition that I am in, I dare not hold my peace, but ſpeake unto you with boldnes in the might and ſtrength of my God, the things which the Lord in mercy hath made knowne unto my Soule, come life come death.</p>
            <p>When I was here about, there came a fat <hi>Lawier,</hi> I do not know his name, &amp; commanded me to hold my peace &amp; leave my preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. To whom I replied and ſaid, Sr. I will not hold my peace but ſpeake my minde freely though I be hanged at Tiburne for my paines. It ſeemes he himſelfe was gauled and toucht as the <hi>Lawiers</hi> were in Chriſt time, when hee ſpake againſt the <hi>Scribes</hi> &amp; <hi>Phariſees,</hi> which made them ſay, <hi>Master in ſaying thus thou reuileſt us alſoe.</hi> Soe he went away and (I thinke) complained to the <hi>Lords,</hi> but J went on with my ſpeech and ſaid,</p>
            <p>My Brethren, be not diſcouraged at the waies of God for the affliction and Croſſe that doth accompany them, for it is ſweete &amp; comfortable drawing in the Yoake of Chriſt for all that, and I haue found it ſoe by experience, for my ſoule is fild ſo full of ſpirituall and heavenlie joy, that with my tongue J am not able to expreſſe it, neither are any capeable (J thinke) to partake of ſoe great a degre of conſolation but onelie thoſe upon whom the Lords gracious affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting hand is.</p>
            <p>And for mine owne part I ſtand this day in the place of an evill doer, but my conſcience witneſſeth that <hi>I</hi> am not ſoe. And here a bout I put my hand in my pocket, and puld out Three of worthie <hi>D. Bastwicks Bookes</hi> and threw them among the people and ſaid. There is part of the bookes for which I ſuffer, take them among you, and read them, and ſee if you finde any thing in them, againſt the Law of God, the Law of the Land, the glory of God, the honour of the King or ſtate.</p>
            <p>I am the Sonne of a Gentleman, and my Friends are of rancke and quality in the Countrie where they live, which is 200. miles from this place, and I am in my preſent condition deſerted of them
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:9007:11"/>
all, for I know not one of them dare meddle with me in my preſent eſtate, being J am ſtung by the <hi>Scorpions (the Prelates)</hi> and for any thing <hi>I</hi> know, it may bee <hi>J</hi> ſhall never haue a fauourable counte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nance from any of them againe, and withall, I am a yong man and likelie to haue lived well and in plentie, according to the faſhion of the world. Yet notwithſtanding, for the cauſe of Chriſt, and to doe him ſervice, I haue and doe bid a due to Father, Friends, Riches, pleaſures, eaſe, contented life and bloud, and lay all downe at the Footſtoole of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> being willing to part with all rather then I will diſhonour him, or in the leaſt meaſure part with the peace of a good conſcience, &amp; that ſweetneſſe and joy which <hi>I</hi> haue found in him, for in naked Chriſt is the quintiſence of ſwetnes &amp; I am ſo farr from thinking my affliction and puniſhment which this day I haue endured and ſtill doe indure and groane under (a diſgrace) that I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it as the welcome <hi>Croſſe of Chriſt,</hi> and doe thinke my ſelfe this day more honoured by my ſufferings then if a Crowne of gold had beene ſet upon my head; for I haue in ſome part beene made conformable to my Lord and Maſter, and have in ſome meaſure dranke of the ſame Cupp which he himſelfe drank of, while he was in this ſinfull world, for he ſhed his moſt precious bloud for the ſal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vation of my poore ſoul, that ſo I might be reconſiled to his father, therfor am I willing to undergo any thing for his ſake, &amp; that in ward joy &amp; conſolation within me that carries mee high aboue all my pains &amp; torments, &amp; you <hi>(My Brethren)</hi> if you be willing to haue Chriſt, you muſt owne him and take him upon his own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>es, &amp; know that Chriſt and the Croſſe is in ſeperable, for he that will live godlie in Chriſt Ieſus muſt ſuffer perſecution and affliction, it is the lott and portion of all his choſen ones, through many afflictions &amp; trials we muſt enter into glorie and the <hi>Apoſtell</hi> ſaith, <hi>that if we be without afflictions whereof all are partakers, then are yee Baſtards and, not Sonnes.</hi> And therfore if you will haue Chriſt ſit down &amp; reckon before ever you make profeſſion of him what he will coſt you; leaſt when you come to the triall you diſhonour him, and if you bee not willing and contented to part withall; and let all goe for his ſake, you are not worthy of him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:9007:12"/>If Parents, huſband, wife or children, lands or livings, riches, or honours, pleaſure, or eaſe, life or blood, ſtand in the way, you muſt be willing to parte with all theſe and to entertaine Chriſt naked &amp; alone, though you haue nothing but the Croſſe, or elſe you are not worthy of him <hi>Math.</hi> 10.37-38.</p>
            <p>Oh my Brethren there is ſuch ſweetnes and contentednes in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying the <hi>Lord Ieſus</hi> alone, that it is able where it is felt, to make a man goe through all difficulties, &amp; endure all hardſhipps that may poſſible come vpon him. Therefore if hee call you to it, doe not deny him nor his truth in the leaſt manner, for he hath ſaid, <hi>Hee that denies him before men, him will hee denie before his Father which is in Heaven.</hi> And now is the time that wee muſt ſhew our ſelves good Souldiers of <hi>Jeſus Christ,</hi> for his truth, his cauſe and glorie lies at ſtake in a high degree, therefore put one couragious reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and withdraw your necks and ſoules from all falſe power and worſhip, and fight with courage and boldnes in this ſpirituall Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, in which Battell the Lord befor your eyes hath raiſed vp ſome valiant Champions that fought up to the eares in bloud, therefore be couragious Souldiers and fight it out bravely, that your God may be glorified by you, and let him onelie have the ſervice, both of your inward and outward man, and ſtand to his cauſe, and loue your owne Soules, and feare not the face of any mortall man, for God hath promiſed to bee with you and uphold you that they ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> preuaile againſt you, <hi>Iſay.</hi> 41.10.11. But alas, how fewe are there that dare ſhew any courage for God and his cauſe, though his glorie lies at the Stake, but thinke themſelves happy and well, and count them ſelves wiſe men if they can ſleepe in a whole ſkinn, <q>when Chriſt hath ſaid, Hee that will ſaue his life ſhall looſe it, and hee that will looſe his life for his ſake ſhall finde it, What ſhall it profit a man if he gaine the whole world &amp; looſe his owne Soule?</q>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore is it better for a man to bee willing and contented to let all goe for the enjoying of Chriſt and doing him ſervice, then to ſit downe and ſleepe in a whole ſkinne, though in ſoe doeing hee gaine all the world and ſee him diſhonoured, his glorie and truth troden under foot, and the bloud of his Servants ſhed and Spilt?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:9007:12"/>Yes without doubt it is. But many are in theſe times ſo far from ſuffering valientlie for Chriſt, that they rather diſſwade man from it, and count it a point of ſingularitie and pride, and ſelfe ends for a man to put himſelfe forward to doe God ſervice; aſking, what cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and warrant any private man hath thereunto, ſeeing it belong<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the Miniſters to ſpeake of theſe things. Yes ſoe it doth, But a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las they are ſo cowardly and fearfull that they dare not ſpeake;</p>
            <p>And therfore it belongs alſo to thee, or mee, or any other man, if thou beeſt a Souldier of Ieſus Chriſt, whatſoever by place or Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling thy rancke or degree bee, bee it higher or lower, yet if hee call for thy ſervice, thou art bound though others ſtand ſtill, to maine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine his power and glory to the utmoſt of thy power and ſtrength, yea to the ſhedding the laſt drop of thy blood, for he hath not loued his life vnto the death for thy ſake, but ſhed his precious blood for the redemption of thy ſoule, hath hee done this for thee, and dareſt thou ſee him diſhonoured and his glory lie at the ſtake, and not ſpeake on his behalfe, or doe him the beſt ſervice thou canſt?</p>
            <p>If out of a baſe and cowardlie Spirit thus thou doſt, Let me tell thee here and that truly to thy face, thou haſt a <hi>Dalila</hi> in thy heart which thou loueſt more then God, and that thou ſhalt on day cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly finde by wofull experience. Alas if men ſhould hold their peace in ſuch times as theſe, the Lord would cauſe the verie Stones to ſpeake to convince man of his cowardlie baſeneſſe.</p>
            <p>Having proceeded in a manner thus farre by the ſtrength of my God, with boldnes and courage in my ſpeech, <hi>The Warden of the Fleete</hi> came with the fatt <hi>Lawier,</hi> and commanded mee to hold my peace. To whom I replied, I would ſpeake and declare my cauſe and minde, though J were to bee Hanged at the gate for my ſpeaking. And he cauſed proclamation to be maid upon the Pillary: for brin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ging to him the Bookes. So then he commanded me to be gagged, and if I ſpake any more that then J ſhould bee whipt againe upon the Pillary.</p>
            <p>So I remained about an hour &amp; a halfe gagged, being intercepted of much matter which by Gods aſſiſtance I intended to haue ſpoken, But yet with their cruelty I was nothing at all daunted, for I was full of comfort and courage, beeing mightily ſtrengthned with the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:9007:13"/>
power of the Almightie which made me with cheerefullneſſe tri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>umph over all my ſufferings, not ſhewing one ſad countenance or a diſconted heart.</p>
            <p>And when I was to come downe having taken out my head out of the Pillarie, I looked about mee upon the people and ſaid. <hi>I am more then a conquerer though him that loved me. Vivat Rex.</hi> Let the King live for ever, and ſoe I came downe, and was had backe againe to the Tavern, where I to gether with <hi>Mr. Wharton,</hi> ſtaid a while till one went to the <hi>Warden</hi> to know what ſhould be done with me, who gaue order wee ſhould be carried back againe to the Fleete, and as I went by land through the ſtreetes, greate ſtore of people ſtood all along to behold me, and many of them bleſſed God for enabling me to undergoe my ſufferings with ſuch cheerefullnes and courage as I did, for I was mightily filled with the ſweete pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Gods Spirit, which cauſed me notwitſtanding the paines of my ſufferings to go along the ſtreets with a joyfull countenance not ſhewing the leaſt diſcontentednes, as if I had beene going to take poſſeſſion of ſome great treaſures.</p>
            <p>After J came back to the priſon, none were ſuffered to come at me out the Surgio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to dreſſe me, &amp; I feeling my ſelf ſomwhat Fevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh I went to bed, &amp; my Surgion doubting the ſame alſo, gaue me a Gliſter, and appointed to come the next morning &amp; let me blood, but when he came, he could not be permitted to come at me: not any elſe, for the <hi>Porter</hi> kept the key, and lockt me vp very cloſe: ſaying the <hi>Warden</hi> gaue him ſtraight command ſo to doe. Wherevp on I deſired the Surgion to go to <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> to the <hi>Warden</hi> &amp; cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tifie him how it was with me, (being very ill) &amp; that he might haue liberty to come at me to let me blood and dreſſe mee, which could not be obtained till the <hi>Warden</hi> himſelf came home. About one of the clock <hi>John Hawes</hi> the Porter came to me, to knowe what I had to ſay to the warden, to whom I ſaid, <hi>Mr. Hawes,</hi> this is very cruell &amp; harſh dealing, that after ſo ſore whipping my Surgio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal not be admitted to come &amp; dreſſe me, nor any other be ſuffered to admini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter to my neceſſities, having not eaten all this day nor the laſt eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ing but a little <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dle,</hi> I hope the Lords will be more mercifull then af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the undergoeing the extremity of my Cenſure to take my life from me, by letting mee periſh for want of looking to, therefore <hi>J</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:9007:13"/>
pray ſpeake to Mr. <hi>Warden,</hi> that he would be pleaſed to give leave to my Chirurgion to come dreſſe me and let mee bloud; otherwiſe I was in danger of a Feaver, which might take away my life; So he wiſhed me to have written to the <hi>Warden;</hi> J told him, if he would helpe me to Penne Inke and Paper, ſo I would. No (ſaid hee) I dare not doe that; Then I deſired him to deliver my mind to the <hi>Warden</hi> by word of mouth; who then went away, and after I was in my bedd, he came to me againe, and ſaid thus unto me: <hi>Mr. Lilburne</hi> I have one ſuite to you. What is that, ſaid J? It is this, ſaid he, that you would helpe me to one of thoſe Books that you threw abroad at the <hi>Pillary,</hi> that I might reade it, for J never read any of them; I ſpeake not for it to doe you any hurt, only I have a great deſire to reade one of them. <hi>Sir,</hi> I thinke you doe not (ſaid J) but I cannot ſatisfie your deſire, for if I had had more of them; they ſhould yeſterday have all gone. J verily beleeve you, ſaid he, and ſo we parted.</p>
            <p>And in a very little while after, came the <hi>Warden</hi> himſelfe with the <hi>Porter,</hi> and J being in my bedd, hee aſked me how J did? Said J, I am well, I bleſſe my God for it, and am very merry and cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. Well (ſaid hee) you have undone your ſelfe with ſpeaking what you did yeſterday. <hi>Sir</hi> (ſaid I) I am not ſorry for what I ſaid, but am hartely gladd that the Lord gave mee ſtrength and courage to ſpeake what I did, and were I to ſpeake againe, I would ſpeak twice as much as I did, if J could have liberty, though I were immediatly to looſe my life after it, wouldſt thou ſo, ſaid he? Ey indeed Sir would I, with the Lords aſſiſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, ſaid I, for I fear not the face of Man; And concerning what I yeſterday ſpake, J did not in the leaſt manner ſpeake againſt any of the Lords, but did open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declare, that I did willingly with all contentednes ſubmitt my ſelfe to their Cenſure; and as for the Biſhops, I ſaid nothing againſt any of their perſons, but only againſt their callings. Ey, ſaid the <hi>Warden,</hi> and thou ſaidſt their calling was from the Devill. Yes Sir ſo I did, ſaid I, and J will prove it, and make it good, or elſe I wilbe willing to looſe my deareſt blood; For if you pleaſe to reade the 9. &amp; 13. <hi>chap. of Rev.</hi> you ſhall there finde, that the <hi>Beaſt</hi> which aſcended out of the bottoml<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe Pitt (which is the Pope and Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:9007:14"/>
State, hath his power and authority given him by the <hi>Dragon;</hi> (the Devill) So that all the power which the Pope hath and doth exerciſe, originally comes from the Devill: If you reade alſo ſome Bookes lately ſet forth by the Prelates themſelves and their Creatures, you ſhall there finde, that they claime their juriſdic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſtanding, and power from the Pope: Now, if their power and calling be from the Pope, (as they themſelves ſay it is) then it muſt needs be from the Devill alſo; For the Popes power and calling is from the Devill; And he cannot give a better power and calling to them then he himſelfe hath; and I pray Sir, if the Biſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury</hi> be offended at that which J ſpake yeſterday, tell him I will ſeale it with my bloud; And if he pleaſe to ſend for me, I will juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie it to his face, and if I be not able to make it good before any noble man in the Kingdome, let mee looſe my life. Ey, but it had been a great deale better, ſaid he, for thine owne particular good to have beene more ſparing of thy ſpeech at that time. No Sir, ſaid I, nothing at all, for my life and bloud is not deare and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to me, ſo I may glorifie God, and doe him any ſervice there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. I aſſure thee, ſaid he, I was exceedingly chidd about thee; and alſo there were old buſineſſes rubd up againſt mee concerning <hi>Dr. Laiton</hi> and <hi>Mr. Burton,</hi> for that Liberty that they had. Wherefore were you chidd for me, ſaid I? About the Bookes, ſaid he, that you threw abroade, in regard you were cloſe Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and yet had thoſe Bookes about you; I would aſke you one queſtion: Did you bring thoſe Bookes to the Fleete with you, or were they ſince brought to you by any other? I beſeech you Sir pardon me for revealing that ſaid I. Then he would have knowne who they were that moſt reſorted to me. I deſired <hi>I</hi> might be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed in that alſo. Ey, but you muſt give me an anſwer, ſaid hee, for I muſt certifie the Lords thereof. Then, ſaid I, I pray you tell their Honours, I am unwilling to tell you. What were thoſe Bookes, ſaid he, that you threw abroade, were they all of one ſort? Thoſe that have them, ſaid I, can certifie you of that. I my ſelfe have one of them, ſaid he, and have read it, and I can finde no wit in it, there is nothing but railing in it. Sir, ſaid I, <hi>J</hi> conceive you are miſtaken, for the Booke is all full of wit; it is true, this Booke
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:9007:14"/>
which you lighted on, is not ſo full of ſoliditie as other of his Bookes are; but you muſt underſtand, that at that time when the Dr. made that Booke, hee was full of heavines and in danger of a great puniſhment, for the Prelates had breathed out more crueltie againſt him for writing his <hi>Apology;</hi> And at that time alſo he was compaſſed about on every ſide with the Peſtilence; Therefore he made that Booke to make himſelfe merrie. But, ſaid he, hee doth not write any thing in it to the purpoſe againſt the Biſhops callings. Sir, ſaid I, I muſt confeſſe, you lighted on the worſt of the 3. And it is true, there is not much ſoliditie and force of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument in it but only mirth; But the other two are as full of ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie as this is of mirth. What, were they of 3. ſorts, ſaid be? Yes Sir, that they were, ſaid I. What were the other two called, ſaid he? The one (ſaid I) was his <hi>Anſwer to Sr. John Banks his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation;</hi> The other is an <hi>Anſwer to ſome Objections that are made againſt that Booke which you have;</hi> But if ever you reade his <hi>Latine Bookes,</hi> you ſhall there finde ſoliditie enough, and the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes and unlawfulnes of the Biſhops Callings and practiſes ſet forth to the full. What <hi>Latine Bookes</hi> be they, ſaid he? His <hi>Fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelluw,</hi> for which hee was firſt Cenſured, ſaid I. What, hath hee been twice Cenſured, ſaid he? Yes, ſaid I, he was Cenſured in the <hi>High-Commiſſion Court,</hi> for writing his <hi>Flagellum;</hi> And after that he wrote his <hi>Apology;</hi> and that little Booke which you have, which were the cauſe of his Cenſure in the <hi>Starr-Chamber.</hi> But haſt thou any more of thoſe Bookes, ſaid he? Sir, ſaid I, if I had had 20. of them more, they ſhould all have gone yeſterday. But, haſt thou any more of them now, ſaid he? Sir, ſaid I, I verily thinke, that if I ſhould tell you, I had not, you would not beleeve me, and therefore if you pleaſe, you may ſearch my Chamber. So I muſt (ſaid he) for the Lords have commaunded me ſo to doe, therefore open your Trunke. Sir, ſaid I, it is open alreadie. Search it <hi>John Hawes,</hi> ſaid he. So he ſearcht it, and found nothing there. Open the Cubbard, ſaid he. So I gave the Porter the key of my Cub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard, to ſearch it, and he found nothing there but my victuals. Search his pocket ſaid the <hi>Warden.</hi> Indeed Sir, ſaid I, there is none in them; Yet he ſearched them, and found as I ſaid. Then he
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:9007:15"/>
ſearched all my Chamber over, but found nothing at all. Well Sir, ſaid I, now you can certifie the Lords how you finde things with me; But I pray Sir, muſt I ſtill be kept cloſe Priſoner? <hi>I</hi> hope, now the Lords have inflicted their Cenſure on me, they will not ſtill keepe me cloſe. No, ſaid hee, within a little time you wilbe eaſed of it; So we tooke our leaves each of other, and hee went away.</p>
            <p>And the next day, being <hi>Fryday,</hi> and a <hi>Starr-Chamber-day,</hi> J hoped I ſhould have had the Libertie of the Priſon; But in ſtead thereof, newes was brought me at evening, that I muſt be removed to the <hi>Common Goale,</hi> or a worſe place, and that <hi>J</hi> muſt bee put in Irons. Well, for all this my God enabled me to keep my hold ſtill, and not to let my confidence goe; For (bleſſed be his name for it) this newes did not in the leaſt manner trouble me.</p>
            <p>And upon <hi>Saterday</hi> morning <hi>Iohn Hawes</hi> the Porter came with the Woman that looked to mee to my Chamber, to ſtand by her that none might ſpeake with me till ſhe had made my bedd, and done other things for me; And he told me, hee was forrie to heare ſuch newes as he did concerning me. VVhat is it, ſaid <hi>J? I</hi> heare, ſaid he, that the Lords have ordered, that you muſt be put into the <hi>Wards,</hi> and kept cloſe Priſoner there, and lie in irons, and none muſt be ſuffered to come at you, to bring you any thing; but you muſt live upon the Poore Mans Box. Sir, that's verie hard, ſaid J, but the will of my God be done; For mine owne part, it nothing at all troubles me; For <hi>I</hi> know in whom <hi>I</hi> have beleeved, and <hi>I</hi> know, not one Haire of my Head ſhall fall to the ground without his providence; And <hi>I</hi> have caſt up my account alreadie what it will coſt me; Therfore <hi>J</hi> waigh not any thing that can be inflicted on me; For I knovv, that God, that made <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> to ſinge in the Stocks at midnight, will alſo make me rejoyce in my Chaines; But it is verie much that they wil let none com to me, to bring me any thing; it ſeemes, they wilbe more cruell to me then the verie <hi>Heathens</hi> and <hi>Pagan Romans</hi> were to <hi>Paul,</hi> who when he was in Priſon, did never refuſe to let any come to him, to adminiſter to his neceſſities; But I vvaigh it not, for <hi>I</hi> knovv my God is and vvill be with me, to make me goe through all my afflictions with cheere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:9007:15"/>
for <hi>I</hi> feele his power within me ſo mightily ſupporting and upholding me, that no condition in this World can make me mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable; And for mine owne part, <hi>I</hi> doe no more ſett by my life and blood in this cauſe, then <hi>J</hi> doe a peece of bread when <hi>I</hi> have newly dyned.</p>
            <p>Afterwards the VVoman telling mee ſhee hoped <hi>I</hi> ſhould not have ſo fore a puniſhment laid on me, but that <hi>I</hi> might have things brought me from my Freinds, <hi>J</hi> told her <hi>I</hi> did not much care how it went with me, for <hi>Ieremies Dungeon,</hi> or <hi>Daniels Denn,</hi> or the 3. <hi>Childrens Fornace,</hi> is as pleaſant and welcome to me as a Pallace; For whereſoever <hi>I</hi> am <hi>I</hi> ſhall finde God there, and if <hi>I</hi> have him, that is enough to me; And for victuals, <hi>J</hi> told her <hi>J</hi> did not doubt but that God that fed the Prophet <hi>Eliah</hi> by a <hi>Raven,</hi> would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve me, and fill me to the full by the way of his providence; And if no meate ſhould be brought me, <hi>I</hi> knew, if they take away my meate, God would take away my ſtomack; Therefore <hi>I</hi> wayed not their crueltie; And thereupon uttered to her theſe 4. Verſes:
<q>
                  <l>I doe not feare nor dread the face</l>
                  <l>of any mortall man,</l>
                  <l>Let him againſt me bend his povver,</l>
                  <l>and doe the vvorst he can,</l>
                  <l>For my vvhole trust, ſtrength, confidence,</l>
                  <l>My hope, and all my aide</l>
                  <l>Is in the Lord IEHO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AHS fence,</l>
                  <l>vvhich Heaven and Earth hath made.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="addendum">
            <div type="introduction">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:9007:16"/>
               <p>The reſt that I intended by the ſtrength of my God to have ſpoken (if J had not beene prevented by the <hi>Gag</hi>) I now forbeare to ſet downe, in regard I heare J am to come into the Feild againe to fight a ſecond battell, unto which time I reſerve it, if the Lord ſo order it that I may have Libertie to ſpeake, I doubt not but by the might and power of my God, in whom I reſt and truſt, valiantly to diſplay the weapons of a good Souldier of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt;</hi> Come life, come death; And in the meane time to what I have here ſaid and written, I ſet to my name, by me <hi>JOHN LILBVRN,</hi> being written with part of my owne bloud; The reſt of which by the Lords aſſiſtance I will willingly ſhed, if hee call for it, in the maintaining of his Truth and Glory, and that which I have here ſaid and written by me</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>IOHN LILB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RNE.</signed>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My verſes are to follovv here.</hi>
                  </p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="verse">
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9007:16"/>I Doe not<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa.</hi> 27 1 2, 3, <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.6, <hi>&amp;</hi> 1.8.6. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51.12</note> feare the face nor power of any mortall man,</l>
               <l>Though he againſt me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ife, to doe the worſt he can,</l>
               <l>Becauſe my<note n=")b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Jſa.</hi> 18.2, <hi>&amp;</hi> 31.3, <hi>&amp;</hi> 28.7.8.</note> truſt, my hope my ſtrength, my confidence and aide</l>
               <l>Is in the Lord <hi>Iehovahs</hi> power, both now and ever ſtaide.</l>
               <l>Therefore my ſoule ſhall never ceaſe, Triumphantly to ſing,</l>
               <l>Thou art my Fort,<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa.</hi> 33 <hi>&amp;</hi> 119, 5.7. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 20. <hi>Revel.</hi> 1.5</note> my ſure defence, my Saviour and my King,</l>
               <l>For in my<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.7.</note> ſtrayts and trials all, thou well with me haſt delt,</l>
               <l>Thy mercies and<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Jſa.</hi> 41.10.13.14 <hi>&amp;</hi> 40.31</note> upbearing hand, moſt ſweetly I have feit.</l>
               <l>Thou haſt in my<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.8. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.167.16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> diſtreſſes great, my ſtripes and bitter ſmart</l>
               <l>So held my ſoule as from thy truth, I never once did ſtart.</l>
               <l>But to thy truth with cheerfulneſſe, and courage have I ſtood,</l>
               <l>Though tortur'd for it were my fleſh, and loſt my deareſt blood,</l>
               <l>When from <hi>Fleet-bridg</hi> to <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> at <hi>Carts Arſſe</hi> I was whipt,</l>
               <l>Then thou with joy my ſoule<note n="(g)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.8.</note> upheldſt, ſo that I never wept.</l>
               <l>Likewiſe when I on Pillary, in <hi>Pallace-yeard</hi> did ſtand,</l>
               <l>Then by thy helpe againſt my foes, J had the upper-hand,</l>
               <l>For openly I to their face, did there truely declare,</l>
               <l>That from the Pope our Prelates all, deſcended ſtill they are,</l>
               <l>And that I might for what I ſaid, make confirmation;</l>
               <l>J nam'd Chapters the 9. and 13. of <hi>Revelation.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Likewiſe I then did feareleſly, unto the people ſhew</l>
               <l>That what <hi>Pocklington</hi> hath writ, is found now very true,</l>
               <l>Namely, that rhey com lineally, from<note n="(h)" place="margin">Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tol. of Bb. Dr. Bast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicks an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: the <hi>2.</hi> &amp; third parts of his Letany</note> 
                  <hi>Antichriſt</hi> his Chaire,</l>
               <l>Even to him that now doth raigne, the great <hi>Arch-Biſhop</hi> here.</l>
               <l>All which I did on Pillary, there offer to make good,</l>
               <l>Or elſe I would looſe willingly, my beſt and deareſt blood;</l>
               <l>Moreover there to Gods people, I did moſt plainly ſhew</l>
               <l>That we have been, and ſo are ſtill, rul'd by a Popiſh crew;</l>
               <l>Therefore againſt them valiantly, we muſt<note n="(i)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Revel.</hi> 12.7. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 15.3, <hi>&amp;</hi> 20.4.</note> fight in the feild,</l>
               <l>And to their Lawes at any hand, not ever once to yeild.</l>
               <l>But from their<note n="(k)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Revel.</hi> 18 4.</note> Yoake without delay, we muſt our neckes outdraw,</l>
               <l>If that we will true Subjects bee, unto our Saviours Law.<note n="(l)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2</note>
               </l>
               <l>Therefore my Freinds, if that you will, <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> here<note n="(m)" place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.29.30.31, <hi>&amp; Ioh.</hi> 2.15.16.</note> enjoy,</l>
               <l>Withdraw your ſelves from theſe vile men, and every Popiſh toy,</l>
               <l>And<note n="(n)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.37.38.39.</note> naked Chriſt be willing ſtill, and ready to embrace;</l>
               <l>Though for the ſame you ſuffer ſhame, and wicked mens<note n="(o)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mark.</hi> 13.13. <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.9, <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.2.3</note> diſgrace,</l>
               <l>Becauſe in him is more content, more full and<note n="(p)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14 16.17.18.27, <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.33.</note> ſweeter bleſſe</l>
               <l>Then can be found in any<note n="(q)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.16.</note> thing; that in the world now is;</l>
               <l>And this I have by<note n="(r)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.67.71.75.</note> triall found, what here I doe declare</l>
               <l>That to the comforts of our God, the Earthly nothing are.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9007:17"/>And he that will not<note n="(s)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.21, 22 23, <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.24, 25. <hi>Luke</hi> 14, 26.27.</note> quite denie, all things for <hi>Ieſus</hi> ſake,</l>
               <l>The joyes of <hi>Chriſt</hi> he neither heare, nor<note n="(t)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 10, 23. <hi>Luke.</hi> 12, 8, 9.</note> after ſhall partake;</l>
               <l>Therefore my freinds if you, your Soules, will Reallie preſerve,</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="(v)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Jſa.</hi> 5, 2.11. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. <hi>Revel.</hi> 14</note> Reject their <hi>Antichriſtian Lawes,</hi> and from <hi>Chriſt</hi> never ſwerve,</l>
               <l>Becauſe the Lord hath ſaid on thoſe, his<note n="(x)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Revol.</hi> 14, 9, 10, 11 <hi>&amp;</hi> 17, 8, <hi>&amp;</hi> 19, 20.</note> wrath ſhall ſurely come,</l>
               <l>His ſoreſt ire, his greateſt ſtroakes, his deepeſt plagues and doome,</l>
               <l>That doe on hand or head receive, the Hell-marke of the Houre,</l>
               <l>Or doe the Beaſt and his image, not ceaſe for to adore</l>
               <l>Thus and much more on Pillarie, there openlie I ſaide,</l>
               <l>Till at the laſt my mouth was gagd, and by them baſelie ſtaide;</l>
               <l>And threatened there once againe, that my backe ſhould be wipt,</l>
               <l>If that my tongue but one word more, againſt Romes Preiſts let ſlipt,</l>
               <l>Thus with a ſtraight Gagg in my mouth, about an houre ſtood I,</l>
               <l>Having my God to comfort mee, in all my miſerie;</l>
               <l>And having ſtood a long time there, J was at length downe brought.</l>
               <l>Moſt ſweetly cheered with<note n="(y)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 6 1. <hi>Io.</hi> 1, 7. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1, 5.</note> his blood, that had my poore ſoul bought,</l>
               <l>And when I was come downe, J cheerefully did ſay,</l>
               <l>I am more then a Conquerer,<note n="(z)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8, 37.</note> through Chriſt that is my ſtay.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hallelujah,</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 19 1, 4.</note> all bleſſing, glorie, honour, laud and praiſe,</l>
               <l>Be rendered to thee my God, of mee<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa.</hi> 34 1, 2, 3, 4, <hi>&amp;</hi> 103, 1, 2</note> and thine alwaies,</l>
               <l>For though that I was in my ſelfe, a Creature poore and<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119, 141.</note> weake,</l>
               <l>Yet was J made through thy great ſtrength, with boldnes for to ſpeake</l>
               <l>It was<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 4, 1, 3, <hi>&amp;</hi> 26, 4, 5.</note> thou Lord, that didſt uphold, with mercie and thy grace,</l>
               <l>My feeble<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27, 13.</note> fleſh ſo that <hi>I</hi> did, rejoyce in my diſgrace,</l>
               <l>Thou fildſt my ſoule ſo full of joy, and inward feeling peace</l>
               <l>As that my tongue thy praiſe to tell, no time ſhall ever ceaſe,</l>
               <l>And now, O Lord, keepe thou my<note n="(g)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>1, 5, <hi>&amp;</hi> 119, 94.</note> ſoule, moſt humblie I thee pray,</l>
               <l>That from thy juſt<note n="(h)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119, 80, <hi>&amp;</hi> 66, 34.</note> Commandements, I never runne a ſtray,</l>
               <l>But unto thee, and to thy Truth, my heart may ſtill be faſt,</l>
               <l>And not offend in any<note n="(i)" place="margin">119, 112, 118, 157.</note> thing, ſo long as life doth laſt,</l>
               <l>And as thou haſt in mee (k) begunne, the ſaving worke of grace,</l>
               <l>So grant, that I thy poore ſervant, may ſtill therein increaſe,</l>
               <l>And when I ſhall lay downe this Houſe, of fraile mortalitie,</l>
               <l>Then let thy Angels bring my ſoule, ſweet <hi>Ieſus</hi> unto thee.</l>
               <note n="(i)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.6.</note>
               <p>Theſe Verſes were my Meditation the next day, after the Executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of my Cenſure; after the <hi>Warden</hi> of the <hi>Fleet</hi> had been with me, from the Lords of the Counſell; and had ſearched my Chamber, it being after noone, and I being not well, writ them in my bedd.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>By me JOHN LILB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RNE.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:9007:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
